In the last lectures, we learned how to pass and extract dynamic route parameters.
Son derslerde dinamik rota parametrelerinin nasl geileceini ve karldn reneceiz.
Now we also see that this somehow leads to issues with our new post route.
imdi, bunun bir ekilde yeni posta yolumuzla ilgili sorunlara yol atn da gryoruz.
The reason for this can be seen if we have a look at the blog container, there where we set up our routes,
Gzergahlarmz oluturduumuz blok konteynerine bakarsak grlebilecei gibi bir kelime var.
we have the new post route which loads the new post component and that flexible ID route.
Yeni posta bileeni ve bu esnek kimlik yolunu ykleyen yeni posta yolu var.
Now I said that I would move it to the end so that it doesn't capture this route here because this
imdi, sonuna kadar ilerleyeceimi ve bylece bu rotay yakalayamayacan syledim, nk
flexible
esnektir.
ID path here would of course also interpret new post as an ID.
dare partisi elbette yeni mesaj bir kimlik olarak yorumlayacaktr.
Now it doesn't capture this route but remember that all routes here are rendered if they match the path.
ilevi adlandrabiliriz Ke dizini kimlii gnderir ve bunu da buradaki kegen KIMLII balantsna balarz.
This of course is a problem here because our flexible path here then is always rendered when new post is
imdi bu rotay yakalamyor ancak yolun elemesi durumunda buradaki
rendered. Now we could of course fix this by naming this posts/:id and also fixing this here in our
tm rotalarn ilenip retilmediini ltfen unutmayn; nk esnek partir Denis her zaman,
link to posts/:id.
bu ii gnderirken elle bu
If we do that, now you see we only load the new post form and if I click on a single post we are at /post1
Bunu yaparsak, sadece yeni yayn yklediimizi ve tek bir mesaj tklarsam bir tane yazm izelgesinde olduumuzu
and therefore only see a single post.
ve bu nedenle yalnzca tek bir yayn grdmz grrsnz.
Definitely viable but sometimes you simply have to use a given URL because your URLs would
Kesinlikle Y yeteneine sahip olabilirsiniz, ancak bazen siz veya L kullanmanz yeterlidir, nk siz veya siz veya baka
otherwise look,
trl grrseniz.
well not the way you want them to look in the end so therefore maybe we have to use that setup.
yleyse sonunda ylece bakmalarn istersen o zaman belki de bu kurulumu kullanmamz gerekir.
We can still tell react router to load only one of all these routes at a time, by wrapping our route
Yine de yeniden ynlendirici ynlendirici, bir kez tm rota tek bir blmn yklemek iin tekrar ynlendirebiliriz,
config here with another component provided by the react-router-dom package, this
burada rota yaplandrmamz, yeniden aktarma ynlendiricisi Dom paketinin salad bir dizi bileenle sarmalayacaz.
switch component.
Hangi bileen.
Switch tells the react router,
Telsey yeniden ynlendirici ynlendir.
hey please only load one of the routes.
Hey ltfen sadece yollardan birini ykle.
The first one actually you find that matches from a given set of routes.
lki, belirli bir gzergah dizisindeki malar buluyorsunuzdur.
So now we can wrap our three routes with switch and the first route that matches a given path will be
Dolaysyla, serbest rotalarmz geile sarabiliyoruz ve belirli bir yola uyan ilk rota
loaded and thereafter, it will just stop analyzing the routes, it won't render any other route.
yklenecek ve bundan sonra herhangi bir rotamz oluturmayaca rotalar analiz etmeyi brakacaz.
With this in place, now you will see that if I go back to home and click on a single post, we load that
Yerinde bunu yaptmda, eve geri dnp tek bir yazya tklarsam bu postay
post.
yklediimi greceksin.
If I click on new post, we only load that form and no longer see that single post.
Yeni mesaj tklarsam, yalnzca o formu ykler ve artk tek postay gremezsiniz.
We also now see that if I change the order and put ID first, that we can never reach new post in this
Ayn zamanda, sray deitirip, nce bu senaryoda yeni postaya eriemeyeceimizi kimlik belgesini koyarsam
scenario
da gryoruz.
and of course we get an error because new post is now treated as the ID and obviously an invalid ID
Ve tabii ki bir hata aldk nk yeni yaz imdi fikir olarak deerlendiriliyor ve akas arka umz
for our backend.
iin geersiz bir kimlik.
So now we see that it does stop after finding the first fitting route which is of course this one with
rotasn bulduktan sonra durduunu gryoruz ve bu nedenle yeni bir yaz hi ilenmiyor.
a flexible parameter and therefore new post never gets rendered.
Dolaysyla, imdi esnek bir parametreyle bu olan ilk balant
So the order is important especially when using switch of course, switch however is important if
Sipariiniz zellikle gei anahtar kullanldnda nemlidir, ancak yalnzca bir rotann
you want to ensure that only one route gets loaded,
yklenmesini salamak istiyorsanz nemlidir.
and of course you can also mix it,
Ve tabii ki de kartrabilirsiniz.
you can put one route outside of switch. So this will always get analyzed at least and potentially also
Anahtarn dna bir rota koyabilirsiniz, bylece bu daima en azndan analiz edilir ve uyuyorsa potansiyel
rendered if it fits
olarak da oluturulur.
and then one of the following
Ve sonra aadakilerden biri.
and then maybe add one more thereafter so you can really mix and match this as you want.
Ve sonra belki de bir tane daha daha ekleyebilirsiniz bylece bunu istediiniz gibi kartrp bunlar eletirebilirsiniz.
That's the cool thing about the router, it's really flexible. So this is one potential set up where we
Ynlendiricinin harika bir yan bu gerekten esnektir, bu sizin iin kullanabileceiniz ya da
can use URLs you want to use and still ensure that we only load one route at a time.
kullanmak istediiniz bir potansiyel olarak kurulmu ve ayn anda yalnzca bir rota yklememizi salamanzdr.